Finding Aid for James H. Robertson Papers, 1956-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James H. Robertson Papers 1956-1987
Robertson, James H. (James Holman), 1915-
0.5 linear ft.
9413 Aa 2
University of Michigan professor and administrator, director of the university's residential college, 1967-1973. Correspondence, 1956-1973, with students and colleagues; speech notes and various other writings; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by James H. Robertson (Donor no. 7619 ) on August 6, 1993.
The collection is open to research.
James H. Robertson was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1915. He obtained his B.S. in business administration from New York University in 1937 and his M.A. and Ph.D. in English from the University in Michigan in 1938 and 1950, respectively. Dr. Robertson's professional affiliation with the University of Michigan began when he was a teaching fellow in the English Department, 1938-1941 and 1945-1946; he spent the intervening years serving in the U.S. Army. In 1947 he was promoted to instructor. After completing his Ph.D. in 1950, Dr. Robertson was named assistant professor and assistant dean of the College of Literature, Science, and Arts. He became associate professor in 1957 and was named associate dean of the College of Literature, Science, and Arts in 1958.
When the university's Residential College opened in 1967, Dr. Robertson was named its first director. He remained in that position through 1973. He was named professor of English in 1969. After leaving the Residential College, Dr. Robertson continued teaching at the university until his retirement in 1983. Besides his teaching and administrative responsibilities, Dr. Robertson was active in numerous college and university committees. He served as chairman of the Administrative Board from 1950 to 1967, as ex-officio member of the LSA Executive Committee from 1950 to 1972, and as a member of the Admissions Committee from 1950 to 1967.
The Robertson papers are comprised largely of routine personal and professional correspondence. His interests in faculty-student counseling, university administrative policies (not specifically University of Michigan), and maintaining friendships with students are documented in this collection. Besides correspondence, this collection also includes notes from addresses given to high school students, university alumni, and Residential College students and parents. His writing is well represented through poems, casual descriptive essays about students, and his published articles. An interesting piece of Residential College paraphernalia, the mock diploma from the College's first graduating class (1971), may also be found in these papers. Included are photographic portraits of Dr. Robertson.
Subjects:
Robertson, James H. (James Holman), 1915-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Residential College.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Robertson, James H. (James Holman), 1915-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal and professional papers
  - Biographical/Vitae (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1973, 17 folders (Box 1)
  - Residential College
    - Mock Diploma (Box 1)
    - 20th Anniversary Reunion, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - Typed Notes, 1957- ca. 1959 (Box 1)
    - Handwritten Notes, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Poems (Box 1)
    - Student Profiles (Box 1)
    - Published Articles, 1958-1986 (Box 1)
  - Photographs: Portraits, U.S.S. Macon Cruise (Box 1)